Guide to the Gwilym A. Price Papers, 1917-1983 AIS.2008.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Gwilym A. Price Papers
1917-1983
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Price, Gwilym A. (Gwilym Alexander)
AIS.2008.04
23.17 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
This collection contains materials related to the work, achievements and leisure time of corporate executive Gwilym A. Price, who was most notably the president and chairman of the board of the Westinghouse Electric Corporation. Price led the company through its expansion into atomic energy in the late 1940s and early 1950s.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Alfred R. Price on November 18, 1991.
Arrangement
The Price papers have been arranged into the following series.
Series I: Awards and Honorary Doctorates
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Interviews and Articles
Series IV: Military Service
Series V: Political and Republican Party Activity
Series VI: Recreation and Leisure
Series VII: Scrapbooks
Series VIII: Speeches
Series IX: University of Pittsburgh
Series X: Westinghouse Electric
Series XI: Oversized Materials
Series XII: Photographs
Series XIII: Realia
Series XIV: Audiovisual Materials
Biography/History
Gwilym A. Price was a corporate executive who served as president and chairman of the board of the Westinghouse Electric Corporation. Price led the company through a time of great expansion in the late 1940s and early 1950s.
Before coming to Westinghouse, Price attended law school at the University of Pittsburgh; he graduated and was admitted to the bar in 1917. In 1920, after service in the armed forces, Price became an assistant trust officer at Pittsburgh People's Trust and later becoming its president in 1940. He left the banking industry in 1943 to become a vice president at Westinghouse Service Corporation, which would later become Westinghouse Electric Corporation. Price was named executive vice president in 1945, president in 1946, and chairman of the board in 1955. Under Price's leadership, Westinghouse expanded its presence in military, atomic energy, and appliance engineering. Though he retired in 1959, Price continued to serve on the board of Westinghouse until he reached mandatory retirement age in 1967.
Price also remained involved with his alma mater, the University of Pittsburgh, becoming chairman of the Board of Trustees from 1959 until 1970. The University held Gwilym Price Engineering Lectures in the early 1970s.
Price won the John Fritz medal for engineering in 1960 as well as honorary degrees from many institutions, including the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie Mellon University) and Allegheny College in Meadville, PA.
Price served one term (1923-24) in the Pennsylvania state house, and remained heavily involved in Republican politics throughout his life, actively supporting both Eisenhower and Nixon in their presidential campaigns.
In his leisure time, Price often went on personal vacations, chronicling his trips in photographs, text, and film. He documented his fishing and recreational trips to the Bahamas; Anacosti Island, Quebec; and Spain with extensive trip logs. Price also traveled extensively for his work with Westinghouse, traveling to Japan, South Africa, China, and the former Soviet Union with other Westinghouse board members and executives.
Gwilym A. Price was born June 20, 1895 in Canonsburg, Washington County, Pennsylvania to John L. Price and Margaret Thomas Price. About 1921, he married Marion Roberts, who taught at Schenley and South High Schools in Pittsburgh. The couple had three sons: Gwilym Alexander Price, Jr. (1922-1983) (a Superior Court Judge), Dr. Alfred Roberts Price (1926-living) (a Physician), and Richard Martin Price (1930-2001). The Prices resided in the communities of Crafton and Rosslyn Farms in Allegheny County and in retirement lived in Rector, Westmoreland County. Price died at Ohio Valley General Hospital on June 1, 1985 following a stroke. Price was buried at the Chartiers Cemetery in Pittsburgh.
Previous Citation
Gwilym A. Price Papers, 1917-1983, AIS.2008.04, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Custodial History
This collection was originally donated to the American Heritage Center at the University of Wyoming at Laramie on November 18, 1991 by Alfred R. Price, executor of the Gwilym A. Price Estate. It was transferred to the Archives Service Center at the University of Pittsburgh in 2008.
Related Material
Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company, Pittsburgh, Pa., Contracts Collection, AIS.1963.24, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
William Wallace Booth Papers, 1922-1973, AIS.1973.23, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Edward H. Litchfield, Administrative Files, 1956-1965, UA.2.10.1956-1965, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Records of the Westinghouse Electric Corporation, 1865-2000, MSS 424, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania.
George Westinghouse Museum Collection, 1860s-2000s, MSS 920, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania.
Westinghouse Electric Corporation Photographs, 1886-1996, MSP 424, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania
George and Marguerite Westinghouse Collection, MSS 432 and MSP 432, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains records documenting Price's business and family life, as well as his civic involvement, particularly with the University of Pittsburgh, his alma mater. Price's scrapbooks document his personal life, professional accomplishments, leisure time, and civic engagement; material in the scrapbooks complements material in all other areas of the collection. Much of the remaining collection is related to Price's time at Westinghouse (1940-1967), including copies of speeches Price gave to Westinghouse stockholders, industry groups, and civic organizations, as well as some of Price's publications and interview transcripts. There is also substantial documentation of Price's time on the Board of Trustees at the University of Pittsburgh, during which the university transitioned from being a private institution to being state-affiliated. Price's leisure time is also well-documented, particularly his hunting and fishing trips.
Separated Material
The following books were transferred to the Archives Service Center printed collection:
A Plan for Pittsburgh's Cultural District, Oakland.
Koerner, Henry, The University of Pittsburgh in Drawings. [signed by Koerner]
Stout, Wesley W. Secret [on the atomic bomb].
Time Capsule [on the 1939 Worlds' Fair].
One Hundred Years in Banking: The History of Mellon National Bank and Trust Company. [cover embossed: Gwilym A. Price]
Nuclear Industry – United States; Electric Industries – United States; Soviet Union; Anticosti Island (Quebec); Pennsylvania; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Photograph albums; Photographs; Films; Sound recordings; Banks and banking -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Education -- Administration –- United States –- Pennsylvania –- Pittsburgh; Fishing –- Canada –- Anticosti Island; Fishing –- United States; Fowling -- Spain; Scrapbooks; Personal papers; University of Pittsburgh. Board of Trustees; People's-Pittsburgh Trust Company; University of Pittsburgh; Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing Company; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous); Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David); Price, Gwilym A. (Gwilym Alexander); Republican Party (Pa.); Nautilus (Submarine: SSN-571)
- Awards and Honorary Doctorates, 1944-1967; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series includes honorary doctorates and other awards bestowed on Price during his professional career and his time on the University of Pittsburgh Board of Trustees. Folders generally include award certificates; some include programs and other related material.
  - Transylvania University, Honorary Doctorate, June 7, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny College, Honorary Doctorate, June 17, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carnegie Institute of Technology, Honorary Doctorate, June 10, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lord & Taylor, Scrapbook from "The Answer of the Atom: Twentieth Annual Lord & Taylor Award Luncheon", April 12, 1957 (Box 15, Volume 1)
  - Bucknell University, Honorary Doctorate, June 10, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Evening Division, Citation, c1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - English translation of Patent of Decoration for the Third Class of the Order of the Rising Sun, by the Japanese government, September 18, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Westinghouse Electric Corporation, Reception honoring Price and John K. Hodnette, April 1, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Westinghouse Electric Corporation, Recognition of Price at his retirement, October 24, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, c1940-1977; II.
  This series contains Price's outgoing professional and personal correspondence as well as a small run of incoming correspondence. Professional correspondence consists of documents related to Price's term on the Westinghouse Board of Directors, as well as some of his work with redevelopment in the city of Pittsburgh. There is also correspondence with others working in private industry and business-related travel. Price's financial correspondence includes correspondence about Price's stocks and charitable donations. Personal correspondence contains correspondence with friends, particularly to accept or decline hospitality invitations, as well as with hunting and fishing partners, and family members. The University of Pittsburgh correspondence comes primarily from Price's time serving on the Board of Trustees, including a term as chair.
  - Business and Professional, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Financial, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Republican Party, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Incoming Correspondence, c1940-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Interviews and Articles, 1949-1956; III.
  This series contains articles written by Price, largely published in trade magazines. It also contains transcripts of interviews Price gave to media outlets and other media productions in which Price was directly involved.
  - "The Incentive Income Tax Plan" [typewritten copy], Fortune, July 1949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "To the Men and Women of Westinghouse" [on Westinghouse's 1948 performance], Westinghouse News, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Operation Economy: For the Long War" transcribed radio broadcast produced by America's Future, Inc., March 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "The Hoover Plan: Performance and Prospects," Dun & Bradstreet, March 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "A Real Answer to Inflation," Trusts and Estates, July 1951 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "I'll Take the Machine Age," [on industrialization and the American workforce], Nation's Business, February 1952 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Industry in 'Man Hunt' for Managerial Talent" [typewritten copy], Electrical News, November 1953 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - [Partial interview transcript on Westinghouse's media holdings and production of household appliances], unknown media outlet, 1954. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Transcript of interview on tax policy and atomic energy], KDKA, Tex McCrary, interviewer, March 1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Script for "Westinghouse Reviews the IUE Rejection" television program, March 8, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Our Exciting Future," Sales Record, April 1956 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Military Service, 1917-1919; IV.
  Includes materials from Price's time in the United States Army during World War I.
  - Officer's Record Book, 1917-18 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Honorable Discharge, November 26, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1918-19 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Application for Lieutenant Rank, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Political and Republican Party Activity, 1953-1980; V.
  This series contains materials relating to Price's involvement with politics and the Republican Party, including invitations to and programs from White House events, correspondence with President Richard Nixon and Bill Brock, then Chair of the Republican National Committee. Also, election tallies from Gwilym Price Jr.'s run for Superior Court Judge, and Gwilym Price Sr.'s formal remarks at his son's swearing in ceremony.
  - Invitation to the inauguration of Dwight Eisenhower and Richard Nixon, January 20, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Book of political cartoons about the Dixon-Yeats contract, signed by both Edgar Dixon and Eugene Yeats, 1954-55 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Program from Dinner With Ike [Eisenhower], January 27, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Invitation to White House reception, December 5, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Invitation to a White House dinner with Admiral Earl Mountbatten of Burma and correspondence from Mountabatten, November 5, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Invitation to the White House Conference on the Industrial World Ahead: A Look at Business in 1990, February 1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Republican Party donor lists, c1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Telegram from President Richard Nixon, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence from President Richard Nixon to Price, December 30, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Invitations to receptions during the inauguration of Richard Nixon and Spiro Agnew, January 1973 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Christmas card from President Richard Nixon and Pat Nixon, December 1973 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Election of Gwilym A. Price, Jr. as a Superior Court Judge in Pennsylvania, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence with Price from Bill Brock, November 17, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Recreation and Leisure, 1940-1972; VI.
  This series contains logs and other documentation from Price's fishing and hunting trips, as well as correspondence with personnel at his regular salmon-fishing location and hand-annotated maps. Logs contain lists of participants, descriptive text about the location and the group's activities, and photographs, often with captions.
  - St. Augustine Sailfish and Tarpon Club Membership, June 29, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bird-hunting Trip Log, Spain, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Bird-hunting Trip Log, Spain, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Salmon Fishing Log, Anticosti Island, Quebec, Canada, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Salmon Fishing Log, Anticosti Island, Quebec, Canada, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Fishing Trip Log, Deep Water Cay, Bahamas, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "Anticosti Salmon Fishing: A Twenty Year Record on the Jupiter River", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence with G.N. Provost (Anticosti Island), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Maps, c1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Scrapbooks, 1940-1970; VII.
  This collection contains eleven scrapbooks. The scrapbooks appear to have been compiled by a member of Price's immediate family and chronicle Price's professional achievements, political and charitable works, his connections to universities, including the University of Pittsburgh, and his recreational pursuits, particularly his hunting and fishing outings. They contain predominantly newsclippings, photographs, and correspondence, but also contain some booklets and bound items that have been attached to scrapbook pages, programs, awards, and other paper ephemera.
  - Scrapbook, 1940-1946 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains newsclippings from Price's banking career, including his election as American Bar Association public relations chair, his election as president of the Community Fund, his election as treasurer of the Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce, his involvement in the war advertising fund, and resignation from the banking industry. It contains congratulatory notes for his election as president of Pittsburgh Trust Bank and announcements of his appointment as Vice President at Westinghouse Electric. It contains some documentation of his work at Westinghouse Electric, including a copy of Westinghouse's corporate name change document, Some of Price's publications from his time in banking and his early time at Westinghouse Electric, materials from the Westinghouse Centennial Forum, and newsclippings and some correspondence relating to the 1946 Allegheny Congenial Industrial Union strike at Westinghouse Electric. There are also newsclippings regarding Price's role as chair of the Salvation Army Maintenance Fund (1941).
  - Scrapbook, 1947-1950 (Box 5, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains documentation of Price's personal and professional work. It contains newsclippings about Price's work at Westinghouse Electric, including new locomotive designs, discussion of tax incentives for business and Price's suggestions for income tax changes, industry in Pittsburgh including Westinghouse Electric, new plants opening, features on Price, Price's speech at the Stevens Institute of Technology (Hoboken, New Jersey). It also includes articles that Price wrote about Westinghouse Electric's corporate report and the country's economic situation, as well as photographs from corporate meetings. There is also documentation of the Prices' personal and civic life, including logs from Mr. Price's 1948 Cape Vincent cruise, 1949 North Dakota hunting trip, 1950 Florida Keys fishing trip, and various leisure photographs, likely from those trips. Additionally, there are newsclippings detailing Mrs. Price's involvement with the Rosslyn Farms Womens' Club and the Prices' charity work at the Salvation Army and American Cancer Society.
  - Scrapbook, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains documentation of Price's personal and professional work. It is largely comprised of clippings and photographs from Price's career at Westinghouse, including documentation of the 1951 Westinghouse Stockholders' Meeting, materials from the Corning Glass Works meeting, articles on his tax incentive plans, clippings and correspondence about Westinghouse Electric's work for the Department of Defense, materials from the dedication of power stations, and materials about the Nautilus atomic submarine. Documentation of Price's leisure activities include logs of his Anacosti (Canada) fishing trips in 1951 and 1952 and photographs of his golf trip to Rolling Rock with other heads of industry. The scrapbook also contains documentation relating to Price's award from the American Society for Metals, and his receipt of the Hopkins Medal from the St. David's Society.
  - Scrapbook, 1952-1955 (Box 7, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains newsclippings and articles about Price's professional achievements, including Time magazine's 1953 cover story on Price, materials from the Case Diamond Association meeting, articles about plans for an engineering center in Pittsburgh, the launch of the Nautilus atomic submarine, and materials about the ground breaking ceremonies for Westinghouse Electric power plants. It also contains clippings and other materials about Price's civic work on the Allegheny Conference on Community Development and the Crusade for Freedom and Radio Free Europe, as well as his commencement speeches and honorary doctorates at Transylvania University (Kentucky) and Adrian College (Michigan). The Prices' social engagements, including a holiday in Dijon and a 1952 Christmas party, as well as Mrs. Price's involvement with the Pittsburgh Playhouse are documented, as well as their charitable work for the Cerebral Palsy Association.
  - Scrapbook, 1956-57 (Box 8, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains continued documentation of Price's work with Westinghouse Electric, including clippings and materials from the opening of power plants and a speech to the Kansas City Chamber of Commerce, from Westinghouse meetings and dinners, and publicity and press photos from Westinghouse events. Mr. Price's civic work with the Allegheny Conference on Community Development and the Crusade for Freedom/Radio Free Europe are also documented. Some of Price's work with the Republican Party is documnted within, particularly his involvement with the campaign to elect President Eisenhower and Price's invitation to the inauguration. There are also clippings about the engagement and wedding of the Prices' son, Richard, and Gwilym Price's commencement address at Bucknell.
  - Scrapbook, 1958-1959 (Box 9, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains materials relating to Price's involvement with colleges and universities, including his speech on atomic power at Dickinson College (Pennsylvania), his speeches at inauguration of Henry Stanford as chancellor at Birmingham-Southern College (Alabama), photos and clippings from the commencements of the Carnegie Institute of Technology and Lehigh University commencements where Price also received honorary doctorates, his involvement in hosting the poet Archibald MacLeish at University of Pittsburgh, letters of congratulations on becoming president of the University of Pittsburgh board of trustees. His work at Westinghouse Electric is also documented, including newsclippings about Westinghouse's future and changes at the company, the Nautilus submarine, and Price's stepping down as President at Westinghouse Electric while remaining Chairman of the Board. There are also promotional and press photos of his work at Westinghouse Electric, including a trip to Russia in 1958, and a brochure from a Westinghouse atomic energy conference in Europe. There are also photos from hunting outing at the Rolling Rock Club and documentation of Price's charitable work with the National Jewish Hospital and his continued civic work with the Crusade for Freedom/Radio Free Europe.
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Volume 2)
    Scrapbook contains newsclippings and other materials about Price's professional achievements, including receiving the Fritz Medal from the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, biographical news articles, the dedication of the Dan E. Kern power plant in Michigan, an article Price wrote in Skyscraper Enginee r titled "Engineers as Administrators." and photographs, including Westinghouse board photos, and photos from the Westinghouse Electric Italy trip. There is also documentation of his civic involvement, including his role in the Pittsburgh Progress General Committee and Crusade for Freedom/Radio Free Europe. There are photos, clippings, and maps documenting his 1959 African safari, as well as a program from the dedication of the Scaife Hall for Health Professions at the University of Pittsburgh. Finally, there are letters from the Republican Party and Eisenhower administration, as well as invitations and signed photographs to document Price's political involvement.
  - Scrapbook, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Volume 1)
    Scrapbook contains newsclippings, letters and other materials documented Price's professional life, including his receiving the Franklin Award from the Graphic Arts Council of Pittsburgh, letters thanking Price for his time on the Westinghouse Electric board, and newsclippings on Westinghouse Electric's work on atomic sea water conversion and the growth in the electrical industry. There are also photographs of his trip to Kingsport, TN with the board of Eastman Kodak, and there is documentation of Price's charitable work with the Salvation Army. Price's leisure time is documented with a log from the Bluff hunting trip, and photographs of a trip to Jupiter River, Ohio. Price's involvement with colleges and universities is documented with programs and ephemera from the dedication of McCormick Hall and Samuel Pierpont Langley Hall at the University of Pittsburgh, as well as photos from Pitt's Fall Convocation, and a program from the dedication of Hunt Library at the Carnegie Institute of Technology.
  - Scrapbook, 1963-64 (Box 10, Volume 2)